so I have another question that's sent
to me by some friend
I'll try my best to answer a friend
he's concerned about
forgiveness trying to forgive people and that's he's
trying to forgive people and that's he's
finding that difficult
so his question is I'm finding it very
difficult to forgive some people in my
life
having done terrible things to others in
the past I know it's also my karma karma
to experience this
well firstly
yeah that's
you might have done some bad things to
people in your in your life in the past
and the result of those actions well
this might be one of those results other
now other people are doing bad things to
you but that's not necessarily the case
but that's not necessarily the case
other people might be doing bad things
to you because that's just what how the
world is
people do bad things to others
because they're there to do it people do
bad things because they themselves are
acting out of lust anger and delusion
and you're in that world with them so
you're going to get affected in affected
by that their actions
so it's not necessarily
from your past actions
and he also says I know that
they will also get the results of their
actions which is true acting out of
hurting others trying to be you know
being cruel towards others well what you
will get
immediate results of that is a cool mind
and is a cruel mind peaceful
is it a happy mind no
it's a
agitated mind
it's not unsettled
a cruel mind cannot be composed settled
at peace calm
equanimous those states are not there for a cruel
those states are not there for a cruel
mind for a person who is cruel
those states of Mind cannot exist
for as long as they are acting out of
their ill will
they cannot have peace so that is
suffering right then and there
right then and there
for that person that is the result
so this person says he can't help but
fantasize about revenge
and you because you can't stop
fantasizing about revenge because uh
something has happened to him
he feels pain
and he continues to feel that pain and
it's that pain came about through the
circumstances of others doing certain
things to him
and now you can't stop thinking about it
the pain is still there he just wants to
get rid of the pain so he starts to hate
on the others and blame them for the
Circ for that pain that he suffers
and if you could just
destroy those others then the pain would
be gone that's that's the kind of logic
there but that's not the case
even if you had to destroy the others
is there still a possibility that others
will now harm you
in the future will pain arise in the
future that you will hate
that you will feel pain in a suffer in
regards to
yeah so you can destroy these people teach
so you can destroy these people teach
them a lesson and then tomorrow someone
else does something
and you feel pain again oh
not even someone else does something
just the weather changes it's raining
outside you feel pain again what are you
going to do then
you can't take revenge on the on the
weather on the clouds
so pain what I'm what I'm trying to say
is that pain is inevitable
that feeling of pain is inevitable
and no amount of changing your external
circumstances is going to solve
that fact
you are a human being who feels pleasure
pain neutral feeling
and feeling pain pain is is this part of
the game
pain doesn't make you suffer it is your
attitude towards that pain
that makes you suffer
there will always be something in the
world that's going to be disagreeable
somewhere along the line
it's going to cause you pain
and if your attitude towards that pain
is I want to get rid of it I hate it I
Must Destroy it you will suffer
so
it's clear what needs to be done
that attitude must be changed
if that attitude is
changed let go of
and you let you endure the pain you
don't try to get rid of it
you just discern it for what it is
painful painful feeling
painful mind stay
don't try to fight it don't try to get
angry at it don't try to get angry at
the world
and what you will find is that that pain
will just change
eventually like it always has it arises
and then disappears
while you're doing this and that and the
other it doesn't matter you can just sit down
it doesn't matter you can just sit down
do nothing and you will see that pain
arise to be there and it will be gone
it doesn't matter what you do
it'll come and go on its own accord
here it's corresponding
to certain things sometimes but
sometimes you walk outside and it's
raining and it's you you feel pain
sometimes you walk outside it's raining
and there's pleasure
so Pleasure and Pain neck feeling
comes and it's just rising and ceasing
on its own accord
alongside everything else you're
perceiving
so it doesn't really matter
where does feeling come from and what's
the difference between perception and
feeling and so on
but really the key thing here is if you
are getting angry
at that pain you are going to suffer
that's a guarantee
if you if you if you lustful for
pleasure you are suffering then and
there but if you remove that
but if you remove that
resistance towards pain
that anger and uh fighting towards pain
you will immediately immediately feel
the kind of release of
release from suffering small releases
you know the pressure will ease off
as soon as you start fighting pain you
you feel the pressure that's when you're
suffering but stop fighting it
but stop fighting it
and discern it see it for what it is
you know when you can do that kind of
thing you stop step back and just have
some faith and step back and stop
fighting it
just basic
logic okay if I'm angry I'm fighting and
suffering so let me stop doing that in
regards to pain
and see what happens you will feel
calmer you will feel a bit you will feel
at peace a little bit at least
and you will start to learn something
there that
I can I can actually do that
I have the ability to endure pain
you know mental pain
without acting out
what if I do this even more
what if I do this all the time
what if I'm mindful of feeling all the
time like this that's mindfulness of
feeling overwhelming
overwhelming
feeling with your discernment so to
speak and your peacefulness
and your non-hate
and your non-lust and your
non-distraction overwhelming feeling
with those qualities
and you will get stronger in that sense
those qualities will be even stronger
and stronger and stronger you will be
able to discern the nature of feelings
eventually
seeing them as anata
but I won't get we're going to talk
about that now
the point is
you don't you can you don't have to
forgive you don't have to forgive the people
because you think that forgiveness is
going to free you from that suffering of
pain but it's not
that suffering of the pain is caused by
your craving against it and no amount of
forgiving others forgiving the weather
is going to solve that issue
you've got to solve that you've got to
stop that craving towards pain
and then it doesn't matter what others
do to you you find yourself in in a
difficult situation where someone does
something horrible too well
when you are above
feeling or you
you can endure feeling in the way I've
described well nothing can get to you then you
well nothing can get to you then you
can't suffer anymore
doesn't matter what people do too
which is the ultimate safety
when you no longer can even take that
feeling personally anymore that's
another not taking feeling personally
that's impossible
but to get to that stage you need to
step back
and see the nature of feeling
you can't just start our feelings on
mine no
no
you take feelings personally
and now you need to endure them first
you need to not act out of them not
trying to get pleasure not fight against
pain and that is going to be difficult
but that is the pathway that you need to
travel it's difficult but
it's difficult but
where you will lead where it will lead
you to is complete
completely being untouched unpressured
ever again by what is felt thank you